Hello and welcome to our lecture on
semiconductors. In this lecture, we
go from tubes to transistors and semiconductors.
So transistors were something that was discovered
at Bell Labs in the quest to build a better
triode. They were trying to build a better
tube. And there are three basic kinds of materials
with respect to electricity. There are conductors
like metal. This is a wire. Inside the wire is
metal. Then there are insulators like plastic.
The outside of this wire is plastic. That's
why if there's electricity inside the wire,
you can grab it by the plastic because the
plastic insulates you. But for transistors,
there's this thing called a semiconductor
and it's certain crystallin materials like
silicon that can be modified by adding certain
impurities. They call that doping. So these
conduct electricity under certain conditions
and hence they call them semiconductors,
sometimes conductors. Here's the basic picture.
of a Nobel prize. You can create a transistor
by taking some silicon with a particular kind of
doping and a silicon with different and touching
them. And so when when voltages are applied to
these crystals, subatomic stuff happens at the
boundary that allows electricity to flow from one
to the other. So it's actually at the boundaries,
right? So when these two kinds of material touch,
that's what creates the transistor. And in the
early days, it was a kind of it was a quest to
take an input and a voltage and make an amplified
output. And and so it turned out that transistors
kind of did that, but you can't couldn't do what
one tube did in a single transistor. And turns out
that the single transistor can be used to amplify,
but it then flips the signal and you got to
unflip the signal back up. And if you look at it,
it's not quite as high quality as a tube. So you
add a couple more transistors and a diode here and
there and a capacitor to affect the them to make
sure that any large DC voltages don't go through
etc etc and some resistors and you add all
that stuff up and you can make a pretty decent
amplifier at that point out of transistors that
you would have done originally with one tube. And
so one of the first things that I saw coming out
were transistor radios. And so what was a radio?
well, used to be something that sat in your house
and you turned and knobs and and whatever and
you went to the store and bought tubes when
the tubes broke down. But a portable radio,
if you could use transistors, they were much
smaller and you could have a portable battery
powered transistor radio. Transistors were
so exotic that in the early marketing of
some of these radios, they told you how
many transistors was in the radio. So,
here is a Sony eight transistor
radio. And if you look closely,
you can see it says eight transistors. Now,
let's turn this on. See what we're going to get.
This is the only radio station that I could get
inside this room, etc. But that is real AM live
radio that is coming to this this radio and being
amplified by transistors. So let's take a look at
what's inside this. So now we have the back off
of it. And you can see here some transistors, some
capacitors, and some resistors just like what was
on that circuit. So um you can see these ones that
have kind of the they're round and they have a
little outline on top. Those are capacitors. So it
has, you know, three, four, five, six capacitors.
They're used to filter out sort of high transient
voltages. Um, and then there's the the transistors
are these little there's the little things that
don't have a circle on the top. They're little
metal. You can take a look at the side of them
to see how the transistors are built. Right
there is a transistor. And it and then there's
some resistors. You can kind of hard to see
them. They're kind of tucked in between things.
And so we have I don't know I can count like
one two well there's eight transistors because
that's what it said it did. And so this is what's
inside of it. It used explicit transistors and it
was able to create a radio. The top this top bit
right here that is the antenna for the radio.
And so there you go an eight transistor radio
probably from the 1960s that still works today.
So for a while it seemed like transistors
were magic and everything that used to
be done by tubes was just slowly but surely
replaced by transistors. The power was lower,
everything lasted longer. You didn't have to
worry about replacing the tubes. But but then
what happened is if you look at the complexity of
that circuit you find that there's too many things
in that circuit and purists who want perfect
audio replication feel like so many transistors
and resistors and capacitors introduce noise and
so there in recent years there has been sort of
a throwback to tube-based amplifiers and so you
can buy these things a brand new one can be over
50,000 and some of them are much higher than that
um And so part of the reason is is that if you
compare and contrast a single tube with a bunch
of circuitry, you can see how it might have some
advantages. So I'll leave it up to the audio files
to decide which is better. Um, also, um, high-end
musicians tend to like amps that have tubes in
them because they feel that they give a more,
uh, a more pure sound. Before we completely leave
tubes and say goodbye and moved on to transistors
for the rest of the class, I want to show you
one last tube. It's called a Nixie tube. And um
it's going to appear later in the class when we do
some digital circuit design. This Nixie tube is a
tube that has glowing numbers. And you can see in
the back I have a working what we call Nixie Tube
clock. And I just want to show it to you to show
how these numbers have sort of a dimensionality
when they're moving forwards and backwards.
Um, but what I like about the the whole thing
is I want to just show you the glow, right? That
there's a certain glow and prettiness about tubes
and those are electrons that are making the the
shapes that glow. Um, and I can kind of understand
why it is that uh people who love audio love tubes
because not only can you listen to the audio,
but you can also watch the tubes as a almost
living analog creature doing your amplification.
This is not a high-end audio class, but this
is kind of where we're going to take our leave
of tubes and move forward into a transistor only
world. So the first thing and this is a graph that
shows input voltage versus output voltage. And so
you could think of the input voltage as something
we're driving on the horizontal axis. And much
like when we talked about making digital tubes,
the earliest kind of transistor was very an
amplifier style transistor and it had a very
much like a tube response and that it had a
nice gradual uh slope because you know you
wanted the amplification of all the different
frequencies and intensities of music to kind of
be consistent as you turn the volume up and down.
But digital transistors like digital tubes wanted
to have a shorter transition. So again, you see
this. Now I'll point out that this is flipped
from the tube one because when a transistor
is doing amplification, it kind of inverts it
first and that's why we had to put extra trans
transistors in to make a real amplifier. But
the picture is kind of the same. You want for a
digital transistor, you want it to have a quick
transition from high to low in terms of the
output. So as the input voltage is increased,
you want it, you know, high high, then snap low
as fast as possible. The other thing you want
is a regeneration thing. So you want it to kind of
come down about onethird of the input voltage. Um,
and so that way that you have if you put these in
a sequence from one to the other, you're kind of
regenerating the one and dealing with that sort
of indeterminate state between zero and one. And
so these are just designed slightly differently
with different impurities and different silicon
and different manufacturing techniques. So over
time there was a couple of different uh kinds of
transistors. uh one was the uh transistor called
NMOS which conducts with the input gate is high
and the POS that conducts with the input is low
and the most modern chips use a combination of
NMOS and POS transistors. As a matter of fact,
there are four general areas of transistor
manufacturing and usage. So the earliest was the
bipolar junction transistor which is more like a
tube with that kind of linear response. They were
fast and they knew how to make them ear in the
early days but they were power hungry and hard to
integrate. And then what we did is we made a POS
transistors which were kind of large and clunky
but they were easier to put together with early u
manufacturing imperfections and they were slow and
then we switched to NMOS faster and simpler um but
both POS and NMOS by themselves wasted power and
about 1983 and like the Intel 486 we switched to
what's called CMOS complimentary metal on silicon
and it was very low power and it was very scalable
and it really from 1983 till now we can we have
pretty much used CMOS and it really has to do with
improving manufacturing over time. So there's a
whole bunch of different eras of manufacturing for
transistors and we built computers throughout
that whole era and uh but today we do CMOS
transistor technology. We'll talk about that
in the next section. [Music] [Applause] [Music]